A Guide to the Ernest M. Gunzburg papers, 1915-1989
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Ernest M. Gunzburg papers, 1915-1989
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 194
1.86 linear feet, 3 document cases, 1 newspaper printbox, 1 microfiche box.
Gunzburg, Ernest M. (Ernest Max), 1911-1990
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mr. Gunzburg in several installments between October 1982 and 1989.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic.
Biographical / Historical
Ernest Gunzburg, a German immigrant, rose to prominence for aiding European refugees resettling in the Richmond area during the era of World War II. He later assisted in the founding and management of multiple organizations in Richmond aimed at community engagement and religious cooperation.
Gunzburg was born in the Free City of Danzig on 29 December 1911. He was educated in Mainz, Germany, and immigrated to the United States in 1935. Soon after he arrived in the United States, Gunzburg worked with the National Refugee Service to settle European refugees in Virginia. In 1939 he relocated to Miami, Florida, to take the position of executive director of the Florida Resettlement Committee. After the United States became involved in World War II, Gunzburg enlisted and served as an interpreter with US Army Intelligence with the rank of sergeant. In 1944, Gunzburg received a commendation for acting as an interpreter for a German parachutist group that had surrendered at Normandy, France.
In 1945, Gunzburg returned to Richmond, Virginia, and became an insurance agent. While in this profession, he continued his efforts to relocate individuals displaced by the war, forming the Friends of Newly Naturalized Citizens. Gunzburg actively engaged in the local community in other ways as well. He helped organize the Richmond Symphony Orchestra, later serving on its board of directors. In 1961, he aided the formation of an interfaith ecumenical committee known as the Commemoration of Faith, which encouraged interreligious dialogue. The Virginia Center for Inclusive Communities honored Gunzburg for these efforts in 1983.
Additionally, he was active in organizations such as the Language Bank, the American Red Cross, the Spring Street chapter of the Richmond Jaycees, and the Richmond Chamber of Commerce. His consistent involvement in the Richmond community garnered him numerous awards and honors. Local organizations frequently requested Gunzburg to speak at events. He used these opportunities to advocate for a Bill of Responsibilities for all citizens to guide their community involvement.
Gunzburg died 22 November 1990 in Henrico, Virginia.
Scope and Contents
The Ernest Gunzburg papers, 1915-1989, bulk 1955-1989, is a collection of materials used by Ernest Gunzburg in his community activities during his time in Richmond, Virginia. The papers provide insight into how Gunzburg engaged with the local community and organizations to promote cooperation and unity ideals.
Correspondence in this collection is primarily with family and Richmond community members regarding a variety of topics. Early outlying correspondence in the collection regards Gunzburg's immediate family residing in Germany and the relocation of European immigrants in Virginia fleeing the disruption and destruction of World War II. The bulk of the correspondence focuses on aspects of Gunzburg's community involvement from 1970-1983 such as the naturalization of immigrants, the creation of the Commemoration of Faith, engagement with organizations such as the Language Bank and the Richmond Chamber of Commerce, and discussions of social issues with local community leaders including Senator Harry Byrd, Rep. Tom Bliley, Senator John Warner, mayors Merrill Crowe and Eleanor Sheppard, and Governors Chuck Robb and Mills Godwin.
The collection also includes various subject files and ephemera, which relate to Gunzburg's community engagement. These include multiple speeches given by Gunzburg, materials on the Richmond Symphony Orchestra regarding its founding and his tenure on the board, awards and honors presented to Gunzburg, audio reels of presentations, and promotional materials and correspondence about the Your Life Today and Tomorrow program, and materials from Gunzburg's involvement with the Spring Street Jaycees.
Naturalization -- History -- 20th century -- United States; Insurance agents -- Archives -- Virginia -- Richmond; United States -- Emigration and immigration -- 20th century.; Richmond Chamber of Commerce (Richmond, Va.); Richmond Symphony
- Appreciation of America Day, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Appreciation of America Day, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- American Red Cross, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Awards and Honors - Ceramic Plaques, 1960-1963 (Box 4)
- Awards and Honors - Certificates, 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Awards and Honors - Letters of Thanks, 1967-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Awards and Honors - Oversize Certificates, undated (Box 4)
- Awards and Honors - Plaques, 1958-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Biographical Profiles - Gunzburg, Ernest, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Commemoration of the Heroism of Faith Event, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence - General, 1943-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence - General, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence - General, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence - General, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence - General, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence - Gunzburg Family, 1915, 1927, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence - Re: Naturalization, 1965-1970, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Drawings by Page, E., undated (Box 4)
- Flyers and Mailings, 1955, 1986-1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Letters of Support Re: Bailey, Samuel W., 1974-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- News Clippings, 1961-1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Naturalized Citizens of America, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Richmond Chamber of Commerce, 1973-1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Richmond Symphony Board of Directors Files, 1955-1961, 1967, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Speeches, 1975, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Spring Street Jaycees, 1977-1978, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Target Roundhouse: For the Future, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Who's Who In Metro Richmond Business, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Your Life Today and Tomorrow - Correspondence, 1975-1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Your Life Today and Tomorrow - Introductory Booklets, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Your Life Today and Tomorrow - Promotional Materials, 1979-1982, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Your Life Today and Tomorrow - "Sixty Years in Sixty Minutes", 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Your Life Today and Tomorrow Slide Presentation Audio Reel 1, 1976 (Box 5, Item 1)
- Your Life Today and Tomorrow Slide Presentation Audio Reel 2, 1976 (Box 5, Item 2)
- Your Life Today and Tomorrow Slide Presentation Audio Reel 3, 1976 (Box 5, Item 3)